<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Impartial account of the horrid and detestable conspiracy to assassinate His Sacred Majesty King William, raise a rebellion in England, Scotland and Ireland and to encourage an invasion from France</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46097</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13312797</idno>
  <idno type="VID">99011</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240886774</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing I70</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13001</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">13312797</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46097)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99011)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 458:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Impartial account of the horrid and detestable conspiracy to assassinate His Sacred Majesty King William, raise a rebellion in England, Scotland and Ireland and to encourage an invasion from France</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Salusbury ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">William --  III, --  King of England, 1650-1702.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99011:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99011:1"/>
            <p>AN IMPARTIAL ACCOUNT Of the HORRID and <hi>Detestable Conspiracy</hi> To Assassinate His SACRED MAJESTY King <hi>WILLIAM,</hi> Raise a REBELLION in <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> And to Encourage an Invasion from <hi>FRANCE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Salusbury,</hi> at the <hi>Rising Sun</hi> in <hi>Cornhil.</hi> 1696.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:99011:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:99011:2"/>
            <head>An Impartial ACCOUNT Of the HORRID and DETESTABLE CONSPIRACY To Assassinate His SACRED MAJESTY King <hi>WILLIAM,</hi> Raise a REBELLION in <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> And to Encourage an INVASION from FRANCE.</head>
            <p>THE Government having had Notice of this Horrid Design some time before, did on Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day <hi>February</hi> 22th. 1695/6;. at Night imploy some Messengers to take up such of the Conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators as they had Received Information against; and the Management thereof being committed to the Lord <hi>Cutts,</hi> he Assisted the Messengers with some of his Captains and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99011:3"/>Files of Musquetiers, and on Sunday the 23th. in the Morning seiz'd divers of the Bloody Ruffians; and in the Afternoon three or four more of the Conspirators were Apprehended at <hi>Chelsea,</hi> and Secured in the Guard-House at <hi>White-Hall.</hi> By this time the News of the Hellish Design had spread over the City and we cannot say whether the Joy of the People for the Happy Discovery, or their Just Resentmonts of the Barbarous Plot was greatest: But the Guards being doubled at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> and all other needful Precautions taken, Messengers were dispatched into all Corners, and the Persons following were seized in a little time, <hi>viz. Charnock</hi> a Papist, who in King <hi>James</hi> time was Fellow of <hi>Magdalen</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in <hi>Oxford; Bertram</hi> a Monk, who was formerly imployed under Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> Secretary to the D. of <hi>York; Grimes</hi> a Monk; <hi>Fitz-Patrick,</hi> an <hi>Irish</hi> Serjeant of <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nadeers; Langhorn,</hi> who had been Chappel-Keeper to King <hi>James,</hi> with three others of that Name, together with one <hi>Lee, Gage, Mackarty, Auberry Smithson,</hi> &amp;c. That same Evening a Council was Summoned at <hi>VVhite-Hall,</hi> the Lord Keeper being present, where the First Three were Examined, Remanded till Monday Morning, and then Committed by Warrant of High Treason to <hi>Newgate,</hi> for Imagining, Compassing and Contriving the Death of the King. That same Evening His Majesty sent for the Lord Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> acquainted him with the Plot, and Ordered him to take care of the Peace of the City, which was accordingly done, and the Trained Bands were raised the next day.</p>
            <p>On Monday <hi>February</hi> 24th. His Majesty came to the House of Peers, Attended with the usual Solemnity, and being in His Royal Robes Seated on the Throne, and the Commons being sont for up, His Majesty made a Most Gracious Speech to both Houses of Parliament, as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="speech">
                        <pb n="5" facs="tcp:99011:3"/>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>My Lords and Gentlemen,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I</hi> Am come hither this Day upon an Extraordinary Occasion, which might have proved Fatal, if it had not been Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed by the singular Mercy and Goodness of God, and may now, by the Continuance of the same Providence and Our own Prudent Endeavours, be so improved, as to become a sufficient Warning to Ʋs to provide for Our Security against the perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Practices and Attempts of Our Enemies.</p>
                        <p>I have Received several concurring Informations of a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign to Assassinate Me, and that our Enemies at the same Time are very forward in their Preparations for a sudden Invasion of this Kingdom, and have therefore thought it necessary to lose no time in Acquainting My Parliament with these things, in which the Safety of the Kingdom and the Publick Welfare are so nearly concerned, That I assure My Self nothing will be omitted on your Part, which may be thought proper for Our present or future Security.</p>
                        <p>I have not been wanting to give the Necessary Orders for the Fleet; and I hope We have such a Strength of Ships, and in such a Readiness, as will be Sufficient to disappoint the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions of our Enemies.</p>
                        <p>I have also dispatched Orders for bringing home▪ such a Number of Our Troops, as may Secure us from any Attempt.</p>
                        <p>Some of the Conspirators against My Person are already in Custody, and Care is taken to Apprehend so many of the rest as are Discovered, and such other Orders are given, as the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Exigency of Affairs does absolutely Require at this Time for the Publick Safety.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>My Lords and Gentlemen,</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Having now Acquainted you with the Danger which hath Threatned Ʋs, I cannot Doubt of your Readiness and Zeal to do every thing which you shall Judge proper for Our Common Safety: And I perswade My Self We must be all Sensible how
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99011:4"/>Necessary it is in Our Present Circumstances, That all possible dispatch should be given to the Businesses before you.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>His Majesty Returning to</hi> Kensington, <hi>the Honourable the House of Commons, as became true Patriots of their Country, Resolved,</hi> Nemine Contradicente, <hi>That an Humble Address be Presented to His Majesty, Congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulating the Happy Deliverance and Safety of His Royal Person,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>After which both Houses Agreed on the following Address, which was Presented to His Majesty at</hi> Kensington <hi>betwixt the Hours of Seven and Eight that Evening.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="petition">
                        <head>The Humble Address of the Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable the Lords Spiritual and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, and Commons in Parliament Assembled.</head>
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>
                                 <hi>Die Lunae</hi> 24. Febr. 1695.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>WE Your Majesties most Loyal and Dutiful Subjects, the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons in this Present Parliament Assembled, Having taken into our Serious Consideration what Your Majesty hath been Pleased to Communicate to us this Day, think it our Duty, in the First Place, to give Your Majesty most humble Thanks, for having Acquainted Your Parliament with the great Danger Your Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Person hath been so nearly Exposed to, and the Design of an Invasion from our Enemies Abroad; We heartily Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulate Your Majesties Happy Preservation, and Thankfully Acknowledge the Signal Providence of God in it; and at the same time Declare our Detestation and Abhorrence of so Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanous
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99011:4"/>and Barbarous a Design. And since the Safety and Welfare of Your Majesties Dominions do so Entirely Depend upon Your Life, we most humbly Beseech Your Majesty to take more than ordinary Care of Your Royal Person. And we take this Occasion to Assure Your Majesty of our utmost Assistance to Defend Your Person and Support Your Government, against the late King <hi>James,</hi> and all other Your Enemies both at Home and Abroad; hereby declaring to all the World, That in Case Your Majesty shall come to any Violent Death (which God forbid) we will Revenge the same upon all Your Enemies and their Adherents: And as an Instance of our Zeal for Your Majesties Service, we will give all possible Dispatch to the Publick Business: And we make it our Desire to Your Majesty, to Seize and Secure all Persons, Horses and Arms, that Your Majesty may think fit to Apprehend upon this Occasion.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>His Majesties Most Gracious Answer was as follows;</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="answer">
                        <opener>
                           <salute>My Lords and Gentlemen,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I</hi> Thank you heartily for this kind Address; on My Part you may be Assured that I will do all that is within my Power for the Preservation of this Kingdom, to which I have so many Obligations: I will readily Venture My Life for Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serving it, and Recommend My Self to the Continuance of your Loyalty and Good Affections.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>The Honourable the House of Commons were so Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for the Preservation of His Majesties Sacred Person, and the Peace of the Kingdom, that before the Address was Presented, they Resolved upon the following Asso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation to lye upon the Table, in order to be Signed by the Members of the House, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:99011:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereas there has been a Horrid and Detestable Conspiracy, Formed and Carryed on by Papists, and other Wicked and Traiterous Persons, for Assassinating His Majesties Royal Person, in Order to incourage an Invasion from</hi> France, <hi>to Subvert our Religion, Laws, and Liberty: We whose Names are hereunto Subscribed, do Heartily, Sincerely, and Solemnly Profess, Testifie and Declare, That his Present Majesty, King</hi> William, <hi>is Rightful and Lawful King of these Realms. And we do Mutually Promise and Engage to stand by and Assist each other, to the utmost of our Power, in the Support and Defence of His Majesties most Sacred Person and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, against the late King</hi> James, <hi>and all his Adherents. And in case His Majesty come to any Violent or Ʋntimely Death (which God forbid) We do hereby further Freely and Ʋnanimousty oblige our Selves, to Ʋnite, Associate, and Stand by each other, in Revenging the same upon his Enemies, and their Adherents; and in Supporting and Defending the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession of the Crown, according to an Act made in the First Year of the Reign of King</hi> William <hi>and Queen</hi> Mary, <hi>Inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled,</hi> An Act Declaring the Rights and Liberties of the Subject, and Settling the Succession of the Crown.</p>
            <p>The House did likewise Resolve, <hi>Nemine Contradicente,</hi> That leave be given to bring in a Bill, that whenever it shall please God to afflict these Realms by the Death of His Present Majesty, the Parliament then in being shall not be Dissolved thereby, but shall continue until the next Heir to the Crown in Succession, according to the Late Act of Settlement, shall Dissolve the same: Which Noble Resolves, and their proceedings thereupon, will render the Memory of this Parliament Sacred to Posterity.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:99011:5"/>
            <p> His Majesty, who hath on all Occasions evidenced himself to be an Affectionate Soveraign, and a true Father to His Country, took so much Care for securing the Peace of the Kingdom, that by and with the Advice of His Most Honourable Privy Council, He Issued the following Proclamation, which was Published on <hi>Munday</hi> about Eleven a Clock at Night.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="proclamation">
                        <head>By the King, A PROCLAMATION.</head>
                        <opener>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>WILLIAM,</hi> R.</signed>
                        </opener>
                        <p>WHereas His Majesty hath Received Information upon Oath, That the Persons herein after named, have with divers other Wicked and Traiterous Persons, Entred into a Horrid and Detestable Conspiracy, to Assassinate and Murder His Majesties Sacred Person; for which Cause several Warrants for High Treason have been Issued out against them, but they have withdrawn themselves from their usual Places of Abode, and are fled from Justice; His Majesty hath therefore thought fit (by the Advice of His Privy Council) to Issue His Royal Proclamation; And His Majesty does hereby Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and Require all His Loving Subjects to Discover, Take and Apprehend <hi>James</hi> Duke of <hi>Berwick,</hi> Sir <hi>George Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clay,</hi> Major <hi>Lowick, George Porter,</hi> Capt. <hi>Stow,</hi> Capt. <hi>Walbank,</hi> Capt. <hi>James Courtney,</hi> Lieutenant <hi>Sherburne, Brice Blaire, Dinant Chambers, Boise, George Higgins,</hi> and his Two Brothers, Sons to Sir <hi>Thomas Higgens, Davis, Cardell Goodman,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99011:6"/> Cranburne, Keyes, Pendergross,</hi> alias <hi>Prendergras, Bryerly, Trevor,</hi> Sir <hi>George Maxwell, Durance,</hi> a Fleming, <hi>Christo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher Knightley,</hi> Lieutenant <hi>King, Holmes,</hi> Sir <hi>William Perkins,Rookwood,</hi> wherever they may be found, and to carry them before the next Justice of Peace, or Chief Magistrate, who is hereby required to Commit them to the next Goal, there to remain until they be thence delivered by due Course of Law. And His Majesty does hereby Require the said Justice, or other Magistrate immediately to give No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice thereof to Him or His Privy Council. And for the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of the going of the said Persons or of any other into <hi>Ireland,</hi> or other Parts beyond the Seas, His Majesty does Require and Command all His Officers of the Customs, and other His Officers and Subjects of and in the respective Ports and Maritime Towns and Places, within His Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> and Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> That they and every of them in their respective Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Places be Careful and Diligent in the Examination of all Persons who shall Pass, or endeavour to Pass, beyond the Seas, and that they do not permit any Person whatsoever to go into <hi>Ireland,</hi> or other Places beyond the Seas without a Pass under His Majesties Royal Sign Manual until further Order: And if they shall discover the said Persons above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named, or either of them, then to Cause them to be Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended and Secured, and to give Notice, as aforesaid. And His Majesty does hereby Publish and Declare, to all Persons who shall Conceal the Persons above named, or any of them; or be Aiding and Assisting in the Concealing of them, or Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Escape, that they shall be Proceeded against for such their Offence with the utmost Severity according to Law. And for the Encouragement of all Persons to be Diligent and Care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in endeavouring to Discover and Apprehend the said Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, We do hereby further Declare, That whosoever shall Discover and Apprehend the Persons above-named, or any of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99011:6"/>them, and shall bring them before some Justice of Peace or Chief Magistrate, as aforesaid, shall Have and Receive as a Reward, the Sum of One Thousand Pounds, which said Sum of One Thousand Pounds the Lords Commissioners of His Majesties Treasury are hereby Required and Directed to Pay accordingly. And if any of the Persons above-named shall Discover and Apprehend any of their Accomplices, so as they may be brought to Justice, His Majesty does hereby Declare, That every Person making such Discovery shall have His Majesties Gracious Pardon for his Offence, and shall Receive the Reward of a Thousand Pounds to be paid in such manner, as aforesaid.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <hi>Given at Our Court at</hi> Kensington, <date>
                                 <hi>the 23th of</hi> February <hi>1695/6;. In the Eighth Year of Our Reign.</hi>
                              </date>
                           </dateline>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Betwixt Monday the 24th. and Thursday the 29th. of <hi>February,</hi> the three <hi>Higgins</hi>'s, <hi>Cardel Goodman, Sherburn,</hi> and <hi>Knightly</hi> mentioned in the Proclamation were taken up, the last of them in Bed Apparelled like a Woman, and his face Painted and Patch'd, which occasioned the Messengers to send for some Women to search him, who quickly discovered that he was none of their Sex.</p>
            <p>The Persons following were also seiz'd either on Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation or Suspicion of being concerned in the Plot, <hi>viz.</hi> the —, Lord —, Sir — <hi>D</hi> —, Mr <hi>Reading</hi> the Player, who had been formerly concerned in the <hi>Drury-Lane</hi> Riot, Captain <hi>O Brian,</hi> the <hi>Irish</hi> Lord <hi>Rosse</hi> who was newly come from <hi>France, Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund Elliot,</hi> Mr. <hi>VVood</hi> and Mr. <hi>Charleton,</hi> two of the late King <hi>James</hi>'s Captains, Mr. <hi>Barrow,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hodges,</hi> Mr. <hi>Green,</hi> Mr. <hi>Fisher,</hi> Servant to the Duke of <hi>Berwick,</hi> Mr. <hi>Boyse</hi> and Mr. <hi>Courtney,</hi> mentioned in the Proclamation, Surrendred themselves. Some <hi>French</hi> Men and Women
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99011:7"/>were also taken up, as was one <hi>Le Grave,</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth VVroth</hi> for Concealing and Endeavouring to further <hi>Knightly</hi>'s Escape, who being in Womans Apparel as above mentioned, gave a very Pleasant Diversion to those who came to Apprehend him, for being surprized as a Dressing, he went to put his Legs in his Petticoats as he us'd to do in his Breeches.</p>
            <p>The first Account of the Plot which is the same in effect with that sent by the <hi>Dutch</hi> Ambassador the Heer <hi>Brand van Cleverskerke</hi> to His Masters the States General, Dated <hi>March 6th. New Stile,</hi> and <hi>February 25th.</hi> ours, was that divers of the Conspirators unknown to one another had discovered the same, and that the Earl of <hi>Portland</hi> having with great Loyalty and Zeal convinced His Majesty, who would scarcely believe it, that his Sacred Life which is so Precious in the Eyes of all <hi>Christendom,</hi> was threatned: It prov'd the Mean under God, whose Providence hath so wonderfully appear'd at all times in his Preservation, to defeat the Wicked and Unmanly Design of those Godless Miscreants who had agreed to Attack the King on Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day the 15th. of <hi>February,</hi> either as a Hunting at <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi> or in his Passage; Forty or Fifty of those Villains being to fall upon the Guards, and Ten or Twelve of them to Murder His Majesty in the Coach. But having fail'd of their purpose at that time, the Hellish project was deserred till Saturday the 22th. of <hi>February,</hi> when His Majesties Coaches being got ready again, and the Guards and Cooks sent before, two of the Plotters who were Spies, and observed every thing that was done at Court, not knowing any thing but that His Majesty was to go for <hi>Richmond,</hi> went and gave Notice accordingly to their Fellow Conspirators.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:99011:7"/>
            <p> In the mean time His Majesty staid and Din'd at <hi>Ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sington,</hi> and sent out some Persons, who found it to be true, that the Rogues had taken their Posts for Execution of the Horrid Design, according to the Information The Conspirators being disappointed likewise for that time, they design'd to Attack His Majesty betwixt the Gates of <hi>Hide-Park</hi> and St. <hi>James</hi>'s <hi>Park,</hi> as he went to Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel on <hi>Sunday,</hi> to kill two Horses immediately, to stop the Paslage, and hinder the Guards from coming up, that so they might have had the Opportunity of Murdering His Majesty in the Coach; but the King staid at <hi>Ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sington,</hi> and Seventeen of the Ruffians were taken up by Sunday Morning▪ three of them being of His Majesty's Guards, and amongst others a Trumpeter of the Earl of <hi>Oxfords</hi> Regiment. If this Horrid Treason had suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded, a Signal was to have been given by Fire from <hi>Dover Cliffs,</hi> that the late King <hi>James,</hi> and others, might have immediately Embark'd for <hi>England</hi> with the <hi>French</hi> Troops; and they were to have been received at <hi>Dover,</hi> or <hi>Rye,</hi> by some Squadrons and Battalions of <hi>Jacobites</hi> and <hi>Papists.</hi> His Majesty received Advice of the <hi>French</hi> Preparations from the Duke of <hi>Wirtemberg,</hi> by Adjutant <hi>Smettau,</hi> who came over in a Fisher-Boat, which was Boarded by a <hi>French</hi> Privateer, who finding nothing in her but Nets, amongst which the said Adjutant lay hid, they let her pass; and the same was confirm'd after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards by Lieutenant Col. <hi>Montez,</hi> of the Regiment of <hi>Belcastle.</hi> It's said that the Assassinates had bound them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves by Oath, six Weeks before, to perpetrate this Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Villany before the end of <hi>February,</hi> that the <hi>French</hi> might be under no necessity of altering their Measures; and therefore, on the <hi>Saturday,</hi> they resolved to put their Hor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, Godless, and desperate Design in Execution upon the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>day,</hi> so that we know not to what Extremities
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:99011:8"/>their Rage might have carried them, had not some of them been taken, and the rest dispersed through Fear.</p>
            <p>On Thursday, <hi>February</hi> 27th. It was published by Authority, That by the Great Mercy of God, a Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery had been made of a most Horrid and Detestable Conspiracy in which many Wicked and Traiterous Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons were Engaged to Assassinate His Majesty when he went Abroad; at the same time a Rising was intended within the Kingdom, and an Invasion from, <hi>France,</hi> to which end divers <hi>French</hi> Troops were drawn towards <hi>Dunkirk</hi> and <hi>Calais,</hi> and Transport Vessels and Boats were got together at those Places, of all which His Majesty had received several Concurring Informations and Advices.</p>
            <p>Other Accounts publish'd that same day gave this further Information, <hi>viz.</hi> that an Exact List of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lotters Names was found in one of their Pockets, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guis'd under the Notion of Debtors to several Sums, and it appear'd that there were more Witnesses for their Conviction than the Law Requir'd. The Providence of the Discovery was observed to be so much the more Wonderful, that the Design could never have been laid in a more opportune Season for the Enemy for had not the Winds stopt the Squadron intended to reinforce Sir <hi>George Rook,</hi> it had certainly been gone long before, and then we might not have had Shipping and Seamen enough in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diness to oppose them, and the time of their Landing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing designed as on the 26th. the Parliament could not have dispatcht the publick Bills for Regulating the Coin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and then we should have been in Want of Money, there being almost a General Stop of Trade and Commerce by reason of the Restraint laid upon the passing of Clip'd Money, and the Uncertainty of the Price of <hi>Guineas.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:99011:8"/>
            <p> There were Advices also then from beyond Sea that the <hi>French</hi> Ships of War at <hi>Dunkirk</hi> had many <hi>English</hi> Officers and Seamen on Board and design'd to put up <hi>English</hi> Colours.</p>
            <p>On the Wednesday before, the Justices of <hi>Westminster</hi> had seiz'd many unaccountable Persons, sent such of them as were sit for Service on Board the Fleet, and discharged the rest.</p>
            <p>That same day the Lord Mayor and Aldermen of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> presented an Address to the King, congratulating His Happy Deliverance, and promising to stand by him with their Lives and Fortunes.</p>
            <p>On Friday <hi>February</hi> 28th. an Express Arrived from Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral <hi>Russel</hi> that he Sail'd on Thursday about Four a Clock in the Afternoon with Forty Eight Men of War in Line of Battle to seek out the Enemy who were said to have Twenty Five Men of War, Six Hundred Transport Ships, and 200 Flat bottom'd Boats, at <hi>Calais</hi> and <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kirk,</hi> with Twenty Six Thousand Foot, Two Thousand Five Hundred Horse, and Forty Great Guns drawn down to the Coasts, part of which were Embarkt, and that the Late King <hi>James,</hi> with the <hi>Mareschal de Bousslers,</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contal, the Marquiss <hi>de Harcourt</hi> and <hi>Lapara,</hi> the Ingineer <hi>Gabaret,</hi> &amp;c. were to Command in the Expedition.</p>
            <p>On Saturday the <hi>2 th.</hi> We had Information that they had Embarqu'd Six Thousand Foot, with some Squadrons of Horse and Dragoons, and had the Cursed Design a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Kings Life taken Effect they designed to have Landed in two places in <hi>Kent,</hi> where they were to be join'd by the <hi>Papists</hi> and <hi>Jacobites,</hi> and intended to <hi>March</hi> straight for <hi>London,</hi> upon some Advices from <hi>England</hi> they had begun to disembark, and but upon fresh Orders from the <hi>French</hi> Court began to Embarque again the Horsemen and Dragoons being for the more Expedition to leave most of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99011:9"/>their Horses behind, and only to bring over their Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coutrements, their Friends in <hi>England</hi> having promis'd to supply them with Horses.</p>
            <p>Captain <hi>George Porter, Thomas Keyes,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Pendergrass,</hi> all mentioned in the Proclamation, were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken near <hi>Leather-Head</hi> in <hi>Surrey</hi> by some Countrymen. They offered to make Resistance at first, but submitted at last and were secured in the <hi>Marshalsea</hi> under a strong Guard, together with one <hi>John Combs</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth Carey,</hi> Wife to one of the Conspirators, and were on Friday Morning removed by <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> to <hi>Newgate. Davis, Boyse</hi> and <hi>Sherbourn,</hi> three of those mentioned in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, were taken up about that same time; the first by a Cobler: And Sir <hi>George Maxwell</hi> was taken up again, and Col. <hi>John Hales</hi> was taken by a Warrant from the Council.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Somerset-House</hi> being the Queen Dowagers Pallace, was Searched for Men and Horses, Captain <hi>Fitz-Patrick,</hi> Captain <hi>Butler,</hi> and one <hi>Standend,</hi> and others were also taken, and one suspected Person was seiz'd in a Cock-Loft in St. <hi>Martins Lane,</hi> there being Five Saddles, and Six Swords found with him.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Gellibrand</hi> the Messenger, did at the same time seize a private Press, with about Fifteen Hundred Seditious Libels, Intituled <hi>A Defence of the Vindication of the Abdicated Bishops.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lieutenancy of <hi>Middlesex</hi> having met at the Duke of <hi>Bedford</hi>'s, Subscribed the Association, <hi>Nemine Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicente.</hi> The Lieutenancy of <hi>London</hi> did also Subscribe it; as did the Justices of <hi>Middlesex</hi> at <hi>Hick</hi>'s <hi>Hall.</hi> And of the Common-Council of <hi>London,</hi> consisting of Two Hundred Thirty Four Members, there was only One who Refused.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:99011:9"/>
            <p> The Association of the Lords House began now to be much talkt of, being nothing less zealous for the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment than that of the Commons, and varied only in this, that instead of the Words, [<hi>King</hi> William <hi>is <hi>Rightful</hi> and Lawful King, their Lordships insert, that his present Majesty King</hi> William <hi>hath a <hi>Right by Law</hi> to the Crown of this Realm; and that neither the late King</hi> James, <hi>nor the pretended Prince of</hi> Wales, <hi>nor any other Person hath any Right whatsoever to the same,</hi> &amp;c.] This Association be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing subscribed by 96, and only resufed by 15, and near 400 of the Commons having subscribed that of the Low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er-House, the King's Friends had thereby a well-grounded assurance of his Crowns being steddy, and a Demonstra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that he reign'd in the Hearts of his Subjects.</p>
            <p>At the same time we had advices from beyond Sea, that the <hi>French</hi> waited only for a signal to sail, and that one of their great Officers had express'd himself thus in a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which was intercepted, <hi>That they wondered they heard no News of the Death of the Prince of</hi> Orange, <hi>seeing he has been so long at the last Extremity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On <hi>Tuesday, March</hi> 3d. We had a Confirmation of the Conspiracy, and intended Invasion, from several Forreign Parts, and that it was no longer a secret at <hi>Paris,</hi> for the <hi>French</hi> King supposing that his Fleet was put to Sea, sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified his Intention to all the Forreign Ministers, to form a Descent both on <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> and to make those Kingdoms the Seat of the War to divert the Arms of the Allies in <hi>Flanders;</hi> telling them withall, that he did not doubt but he should oblige the Confederates to a speedy Peace by this Method; for he had so well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider'd all Objections that could be offer'd against it, that it was morally impossible (bating Wind and Weather) that it could ever miscarry: And this following Account is given of it, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:99011:10"/>
            <p> That his most Christian Majesty, in <hi>January</hi> last, held a Cabinet Council at <hi>Marli,</hi> where the Scheme or Project of the Invasion had its first rise, grounded upon the Assurance that 500 Merchant Ships were bound to the <hi>Streights,</hi> and a great Squadron for their Convoy was going to reinforce Sir <hi>George Rook,</hi> which would most certainly have left the Channel in a manner naked, both of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners and Shipping, at least not sufficient to have with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood Monsieur <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>smond</hi>'s and <hi>Dubart</hi>'s Squadrons: The calmness of the Season and advance of the Spring not a little contributing to the Undertaking: Together with the Ferment that the People were in upon Account of the alteration of the Coin, and uncertainty of Guinea's; as also the Misunderstanding between the two Nations about the Proceedings of the Scotch <hi>East-India</hi> Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: And that which weighed most with the French King was, that there were but few Regular Troops left in <hi>England,</hi> and those also in remote Places, whereby they could make but little Opposition: All which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing premised, the Design was fully concluded the 6th. <hi>ultimo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Never was so great an Undertaking carried on with more Secrecy; for the French King wrote the Dispatches with his own hand, and sent for the Mareschal <hi>de Bouslers</hi> from <hi>Flanders</hi> to advise with, who mightily approved the Undertaking: Whereupon King <hi>James</hi> was forthwith sent for, and made privy to the Secret, who promised to go in Person; the French King assuring him, That he never saw a fairer Prospect of Success in any Undertaking in his Life: And thereupon the Duke of <hi>Berwick,</hi> with four of the late King's confiding Domesticks, were sent to <hi>England,</hi> as well to procure a sufficient Number of Rus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sians to murder the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> as they call him, as to know what Assistance their Friends could give them in both the Kingdoms.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:99011:10"/>
            <p> Then Orders were sent to all the Ports to hasten the Transport Ships and Men of War, for the intended Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion: And the French King being informed that all things were in a readiness at <hi>Calais, Bullen,</hi> and <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> he went on the 17th. of the last month to St. <hi>Germains,</hi> where he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to Kings <hi>James</hi> 100000 <hi>l.</hi> in Gold, desiring him to hasten his Departure, and took his farewell of him, wish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him a prosperous and successful Undertaking, assuring him at the same time, that as soon as he had posted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self on the other side of the Water, he would supply him with more Troops, to enable him to perfect the Work. King <hi>James</hi> spent the remainder of that day in visiting, and amongst others, the Pope's Nuncio, who pronounc'd a Solemn Benediction upon his Undertaking; and the next day he set forward in a Calash to St. <hi>Dennis,</hi> where calling for a Publick Notary, he caused him to draw up an Instrument, or Mortgage, of the three Crowns, for repaying King <hi>Lewis</hi> the said 100000 <hi>l.</hi> then lent him; also all the Money had of him since his being in <hi>France,</hi> together with the charge of the present Expedition: And while it was a writing, a Servant of the Duke of <hi>Berwick</hi>'s arrived, and told King <hi>James</hi> that his Master was but a little behind, and in an hour after the said Duke came thither from <hi>England,</hi> after 14 days absence from St. <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains,</hi> and signified, that the English Nation was in a profound security, the People generally dissatisfied, and willing to receive him as their lawful Sovereign; to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm which, he brought him a great many Letters, and par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cularly from some of the <hi>Scotch</hi> Nobility, assuring him, that they would assist with 12000 Men upon his Landing with a <hi>French</hi> Force there.</p>
            <p>King <hi>James</hi> forthwith dispatched the Duke to the <hi>French</hi> King with his Letters, and the Verbal Account he brought from <hi>England,</hi> together with the Mortgage aforesaid: The Duke found his Majesty at <hi>Crolssy,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99011:11"/>upon some new Measures were taken, for King <hi>Lewis</hi> caused a Declaration to be Penned, and Printed for him, Granting a General Amnesty to all his English and Scoth Subjects that did not oppose him, promising a Relaxation from Taxes, a perpetual Parliament, and the preserva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Protestant Religion. All which being done, King <hi>James</hi> went to <hi>Montrevil,</hi> and arrived on the 2 <hi>d.</hi> Instant, <hi>Stilo Novo,</hi> at <hi>Calais,</hi> where the Mareschal <hi>de Bouslers</hi> met, and acquainted him that the Embarcation was ready, consisting of twenty four Battalions of Foot, and seven Squadrons of Horse, and five of Dragoons, but the latter were order'd to leave their Horses behind, being assured by the Duke of <hi>Berwick,</hi> that they would be remounted in <hi>England,</hi> and they had with them Cannon, Ammunition, Money, Provisions, Stores, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Men of War, their Convoy, being to be commanded by Vice Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral <hi>Gabaret,</hi> M. <hi>de Nesmond</hi> and <hi>Dubart,</hi> and the Army to be conducted by the Marquess <hi>de Harcourt,</hi> one Mares<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal de Camp, and four Brigadiers, and <hi>Lapara</hi> the chief Engineer. Accordingly they embarked that day, being the day before this was publickly known here, and they put out to Sea from <hi>Calais,</hi> &amp;c. about 300 Sail, but the Wind shifting contrary, they were obliged to return in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Port, and disembark; the Providence of which is the more observable, since, had they gone forward, we might have been under some surprize, neither our Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, nor Land Forces being in a readiness to oppose them.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Sunday</hi> the 30th. we had three Consecutive Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presses; the first from Admiral <hi>Russel,</hi> of the 28th. <hi>ult.</hi> off of <hi>Gravelin,</hi> signifying, that he was joyn'd by ten Men of War, and the <hi>Martin</hi> Ketch from <hi>Plymouth,</hi> so that he was 60 Sail: That he had detached the Lord <hi>Berkley</hi> with a Squadron to observe what Men of War and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sport-Ships were about <hi>Dunkirk;</hi> and that his Lordship
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99011:11"/>had sent him word, That he discern'd seventeen or eighteen great ships, which were got so far among the Flemish Sands to secure themselves, as that it would be hard for them to get off, or to make their way into <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kirk,</hi> without throwing their great Guns over-board; and not so neither, without a Spring Tide: So that he hoped to give a good account of them as soon as the Bomb-boats and Fire ships arrive: That Sir <hi>Cloudsley Shovel</hi> being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tach'd with another Squadron to the Bay of <hi>Bullen,</hi> found none of the Enemy therein, they having crouded their ships into the Bay of <hi>Calais</hi> for more safety, where they appear'd like a Wood, and were raising Batteries for their defence. The Admiral added, that he doubted not of destroying most of them when the Bomb-boats and Fire-ships came up, or, at least, to prevent their putting to Sea on their intended Design; and, that having more ships than enough, he was quitting the Victory for one of a lesser rate, and design'd to send the great ships into the <hi>Downs,</hi> till he had further occasion for them.</p>
            <p>The second Express was brought from Sir <hi>George Rook,</hi> by Captain <hi>Millison,</hi> who arriv'd on board the <hi>Portsmouth,</hi> at <hi>Spithead:</hi> He left Sir <hi>George</hi> at <hi>Cadiz-Bay</hi> on the 13th. of <hi>February,</hi> Old Style, with his Top-sails loose, ready to sail, and says, the French could not possible set out from <hi>Thoulon</hi> before the 23 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third Express was brought by the Earl of <hi>Rum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,</hi> from <hi>Dover,</hi> with an account that the Militia of <hi>Kent</hi> were in Arms, guarded all Passes, examined all Travellers, had seized five whom they had reason to suspect, and sent them to <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On <hi>Thursday,</hi> March 5th. We had a further Account of the Duke of <hi>Berwick</hi>'s Negotiation, <hi>viz.</hi> That he was to sollicit such of the <hi>Scots</hi> Nobility as were in the late King <hi>James</hi>'s Interests, to appear at the Head of the Malecontents, who were to raise a Rebellion in <hi>Scotland,</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:99011:12"/>upon the News of King <hi>James</hi>'s arrival in <hi>England,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving promised them some of the best <hi>French</hi> Officers to assist in commanding their Troops, and that the Forces designed for the Descent should be ready to sail on the 4th. or 5th. of <hi>March, S. N.</hi> with a sufficient Convoy. His Majesty King <hi>William</hi> had at the same time Advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces by several Couriers from beyond Sea, that the <hi>French</hi> talkt of making a Descent on all the three Kingdoms, and that <hi>Mounsieur de Bouslers</hi> was to command in one of the said Expeditions. Information was also given, that the late King <hi>James</hi> had agreed to put three Cautionary Towns for <hi>England,</hi> one for <hi>Scotland,</hi> and one for <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> into the Hands of the <hi>French</hi> King, for performance of Articles, and repayment of the Money borrowed, and the Charges he had put him to, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King engaging at the same time to use his utmost endeavours to kindle a War in <hi>Germany,</hi> either by fomenting the Differences betwixt the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Holstein,</hi> or by heightening the Jealousies betwixt the Protestants and Papists about the Ninth Electorate, and so to improve the Differences betwixt the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and the <hi>Dutch,</hi> about denying <hi>Monsieur Schonenburg</hi> the usual Priviledges of other Forreign Ministers; and to allarm the Princes of <hi>Italy</hi> and the <hi>Swiss Cantons</hi> by attacqueing <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neva,</hi> that the Allies should not be capable of giving any assistance to <hi>England;</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King assuring King <hi>James</hi> that the Emperor was very unsuccessful in his Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vies both of Men and Money, and that he would take care to create the King of <hi>Spain</hi> work enough in <hi>Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonia,</hi> and to raise Jealousies betwixt the Crowns of <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal</hi> and <hi>Spain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A further Discovery of the Designs of the Plotters at home was then also the common Subject of Discourse, as that upon the perpetration of the Horrid Murder, and Landing of the <hi>French,</hi> there was to be a Rendesvouz of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:99011:12"/>the Disaffected Party upon <hi>Black-heath,</hi> who were either to have march'd forward to join the Enemy, or to have advanced towards <hi>London,</hi> as should have been found most convenient: That the City and Suburbs were at the same time to have been set on Fire in different places; that during the Consternation, and under pretence of assisting to extinguish the Flames, and prevent Disorders, the <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobites</hi> and <hi>Papists</hi> (who were in great Numbers about the City) should have had the opportunity of assembling to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, seizing the <hi>Tower,</hi> turning the Cannon against the Citizens, if they had attempted any Resistance, surprizing the Guards and Cannon at <hi>White-Hall</hi> and in St. <hi>James</hi>'s <hi>Park,</hi> and of rendering themselves Masters of the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But by the Goodness of God, who hath so frequently delivered <hi>England</hi> from the Hellish Conspiracies of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists, and such dissolute Men as are a scandal to the Name of Protestants, defeated and broke all those Measures, and when they thought to have been triumphant over us with Fire and Sword, abundance of the Horrid Conspirators and other suspected Persons were taken up every day, and amongst others the Duke of <hi>Beaufort</hi>'s Steward, the Earl of <hi>Feversham</hi>'s Gentleman of the Horse; Mr. <hi>Burrows</hi> of the <hi>Temple;</hi> Dr. <hi>Lake,</hi> Minister of St. <hi>Mary Hill,</hi> in the City; Mr. <hi>Hales,</hi> the Excise-man of <hi>Chelsea;</hi> Major <hi>Clif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> and <hi>Durance</hi> a Priest, one of those mentioned in the Proclamation; so that 14 of the 29 therein mentioned were at that time in Custody.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Tuesday</hi> the 3 <hi>d.</hi> an Express arrived with an account that the Privateers of <hi>Jersey</hi> and <hi>Guernsey</hi> had taken 18 <hi>French</hi> Ships laden with Wine, Brandy, Ammunition and Provision, for the Fleet and Forces at <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> or those designed for <hi>Scotland,</hi> it having been given out for some dayes together, that part of the <hi>French</hi> Fleet and Forces were sail'd towards <hi>Scotland,</hi> but it was afterwards found
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99011:13"/>to be a mistake, and that a Fleet of <hi>Swedes</hi> and <hi>Danes,</hi> homeward bound from <hi>France,</hi> had given rise to that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port.</p>
            <p>At the same time we had advices from beyond Sea, that the French Court had recieved the Mortifying News of the Miscarriage of their Design, and that there was a mighty Joy in <hi>Holland,</hi> and at the Elector of <hi>Bavaria</hi>'s Court in <hi>Brussels,</hi> for the happy Discovery of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiracy against his Majesty of <hi>Great Brittain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There were now, as there had been for some time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, Guards placed in all Roads, and no Person suffered to travel without a Pass: Charge was also given to all Inn-keepers to part with no serviceable Horses out of their Stables, without an Order from the next Justice of the Peace; and about 500 belonging to suspected Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons were seiz'd in and about the City.</p>
            <p>An Owler accus'd of carrying over the Duke of <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick,</hi> was taken likewise about this time, and it was the Subject of Discourse, that Warrants were issued for seiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing above an hundred Persons, on Captain <hi>Porters</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession: Sir <hi>Richard Hart</hi> was the seiz'd, and Sir <hi>John Knight</hi> of <hi>Bristol,</hi> noted for a disaffected Speech in the last Parliament, was sought after. There was such care taken for the defence of our Coasts, that eight Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritime Counties were covered by the Militia and other Troops.</p>
            <p>The Sessions-Court at the <hi>Old-Baily</hi> was adjourned, but the Grand Juries of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Middlesex</hi> continued, and a Special Commission of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer</hi> was pass'd for trying the Conspirators, wherein several of the Lords and Commons were inserted, with the two Lord Chief Justices <hi>Holt</hi> and <hi>Treby,</hi> the Lord Chief Baron <hi>Ward,</hi> Mr. <hi>Justice Powel,</hi> Mr. <hi>Justice Nevil,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Justice Rooksby.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Inland Posts brought an Account from all the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:99011:13"/>Cities and Corporations of the Kingdom, that the People expressed their utmost Abhorrence of the Plot; and that the Magistrates caus'd the Gates to be shut, and strict Search to be made for the Conspirators, and other disaffected Persons.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Wednesday</hi> the 4th. the Non-Conformist Ministers of <hi>London</hi> waited upon his Majesty; and Mr. <hi>How</hi> being Spokes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, presented a very Loyal and affectionate Address, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulating his Majesty's happy Deliverance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which his Majesty accepted very favourably, assuring them of his Protection, and Kindness</p>
            <p>That same Day we had an Account by an Express from Admiral <hi>Russel,</hi> which arrived the Night before, that 17 of the French Men of War had retired into the Flemish Road, and were taking out their Guns, cutting down their Masts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that so they might be light and get into <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kirk;</hi> and that he had detached Sir <hi>Cl. Shovel,</hi> with a Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron of Men of War and some Fireships, to annoy them if possible.</p>
            <p>We had also this following Information from beyond Sea, amongst others at that time, <hi>viz.</hi> That King <hi>James</hi> had agreed with the French King to renounce all the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tensions and Claims which he or his Ancestors had, or ought to have, to the Crown of <hi>France;</hi> and that as soon as he could do it with Safety, he should leave the same out of his Title, and the Arms of <hi>France</hi> out of his Escutcheon, on Condition that the French King and his Heirs should from time to time assist him and his Heirs against the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions of their Subjects, when their Assistance should be required. That a Jubilee had been publish'd at <hi>Paris,</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding all Revelling and Excesses, that they might apply themselves wholly to pray for Success to K. <hi>James.</hi> That the Duke of <hi>Berwick,</hi> on his return from <hi>Versailles</hi> to <hi>Calais,</hi> took leave of the French King, telling him, That he hop'd
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:99011:14"/>to return in three Months time as Ambassador Extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary from his Father, to thank him for all his Royal Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours. That amongst other Things signed by King <hi>James</hi> before the Publick Notary, there was a List of the Jewels which he had pawn'd to some French Merchants for 450000 Livres; that his Queen was retired to the Nunne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Chaillot,</hi> expecting the Event of the Expedition: That 200 Artillery-Horses, and 20 Mortars were arrived at <hi>Calais</hi> for his Enterprize. That the <hi>French</hi> had taken such Care to stop all Advices, that they hop'd to surprize us. That a French Spy-Boat, having landed some Men in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> brought Advice to St. <hi>Maloes,</hi> that there was a great Disposition in that Kingdom towards an Insurrection; and that besides the 100000 <hi>l.</hi> given to King <hi>James</hi> when he went from St. <hi>Germains,</hi> such another Summ was remitted to him at <hi>Calais.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Letters from the <hi>Hague</hi> by that same Post inform'd us, That upon the News of K. <hi>James</hi>'s arrival at <hi>Calais,</hi> the States-Gen. assembled frequently, and hasten'd the Equipment of their Fleet with wonderful expedition: That K. <hi>James</hi> with his Guards and General Officers were ready to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bark, and staid only for the arrival of the <hi>Brest</hi> Squadron to join <hi>Gabarot</hi> and <hi>Dubart.</hi> Some English Men were taken up at <hi>Rotterdam</hi> on Suspicion at the same time. And it was confir'd by French Letters, that the Design against <hi>England</hi> was formed at St. <hi>Germains</hi> in <hi>January,</hi> by a select Council of 26, as the only thing that could put an End to the War.</p>
            <p>A Flying Post brought Advice at the same time from <hi>Scotland,</hi> that the Government there had put the Country in a Posture of Defence, secur'd the Earl of <hi>Hume,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther disaffected Persons, and had taken such Precautions, as they would be able to crush any Commotion in its Birth.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:99011:14"/>
            <p> By this time <hi>Newgate</hi> was so full of suspected Persons and Conspirators, that the City appointed some of the Train'd-Bands to guard it. Amongst the Prisoners there was the E. of <hi>Castlemain,</hi> who had some time before surrendred him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, in order to reverse an Outlawry of High-Treason that stands against him.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Dutch,</hi> who abound in Sculptures upon such Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, were not wanting on this, having, as we were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, engraven a Fleet of Ships by the French Shoar, and King <hi>James</hi> with his Hands bound, drawn on Board by the Pope and Cardinals, to commence a Holy War, und the French King behind pushing him forward, with a Label issuing from King <hi>James</hi>'s Mouth, having these Words upon it, <hi>Frustra tentare, nocebit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About the same time we had Advice, that the <hi>French</hi> were disembarking their Men at <hi>Calais,</hi> because they found that they could not go on with the Descent.</p>
            <p>Information being given against Sir <hi>William Perkins,</hi> Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sengers were sent to search his House, within two Miles of <hi>Coventry,</hi> where Arms and other Accoutrements, sufficient for a Troop of Horse, were found hid under the Garden Wall: They had been sent to Mr. <hi>Haywood</hi>'s, Brother-in-Law to <hi>Charnock,</hi> who not thinking it safe to keep them, they were return'd and buried there: Mr. <hi>Haywood</hi> was thereupon committed to <hi>Warwick</hi> Gaol; and the enraged Populace pull'd down Sir <hi>William</hi>'s House, and destroyed his Gardens, saying, That Traitors should no more find any retiring Place there.</p>
            <p>The Justices of <hi>Middlesex,</hi> who had not sign'd the Asso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation, were re-summoned to appear at <hi>Hicks</hi>'s <hi>Hall.</hi> And the Earl of <hi>Arran,</hi> eldest Son to the late Duke of <hi>Hamil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> surrendred himself: It being said, that he had his Choice, of being confin'd to his own House, or of going to <hi>Holland,</hi> upon his Parole of Honour, not to stir out of the States Dominions till <hi>October</hi> following.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:99011:15"/>
            <p> Dr. <hi>Paterson,</hi> late Archbishop of <hi>Glasgow</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> Dr. <hi>Monro,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Mackintosh,</hi> two more of the Scots outed Clergy, were taken up sometime before, by an Order from the Secretary of State for <hi>Scotland.</hi> Mr. <hi>Pawlet,</hi> at the Blue Posts in the <hi>Hay-Market,</hi> was also taken up about that time; and the Lord <hi>B</hi> — was committed to the <hi>Tower.</hi> A Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeant of the Foot-Guards was then also taken into Custody, being accused of having receiv'd King <hi>James</hi>'s Pay, and to have promis'd to let in King <hi>James</hi>'s, or the French Forces, to surprize the Guards at <hi>White-Hall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On <hi>Thursday, March</hi> 5. we had a further Account of the Plot from abroad, publish'd to this Effect, That the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of Jesuits at <hi>Paris</hi> were concern'd in it; that two of their Number, and 100 Secular Priests in Officers Habit, were to attend the late King over hither; that they were to have brought a considerable Number of consecrated Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licts with them, and amongst others, the Image of St. <hi>Victor,</hi> which was sent into <hi>France</hi> by the Queen of <hi>Poland,</hi> with a Legend of its miraculous Effects against the Infidels; and therefore they thought it might be no less Efficacious against Hereticks. That the late King's Followers were so confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of Success, that they talk'd of taking Debentures up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on such and such Estates in <hi>England;</hi> that there was scarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Place about Court which the late King had not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised to one or other of his Retinue; and that the Jesuits had begg'd <hi>Chelsea-College</hi> for their Society, that they might be near the King, to give him Counsel in his important Affairs. That most of the Religious Houses in <hi>Paris</hi> had ventured more or less in the Expedition. That the <hi>Town-House</hi> there had advanced 300000 Livres on an Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment sign'd by King <hi>James,</hi> to re-pay them in six Months at a certain Interest: That many of the Bankers and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of <hi>Paris</hi> had ventured considerably in Goods for <hi>England,</hi> sending either their Sons or chief Servants Supercar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go; K. <hi>James</hi> having promis'd them freedom from Customs in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:99011:15"/>
               <hi>England,</hi> and the French King having promis'd them the like for the Returns they made to <hi>France.</hi> Such of the late Kings Followers as had Money, did also convert the same in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to those Commodities, which they thought would yield the best Price in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The same Letters added, That they relied much upon the provocation given to the <hi>Scots</hi> about their <hi>East-India</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and the Resolution of the People to maintain their Act; And that they were much animated to the Enterprize, by the Advices which the <hi>Jacobites</hi> sent them from <hi>England</hi> of the mighty Discontents here because of the Decay of Trade; and particularly, of the huge Sums which they had sent them an Account of, that were lost by the <hi>East-India, African,</hi> and <hi>Hudson</hi>'s-Bay Companies, besides the Losses of those concerned in <hi>Barbadoes, Pensylvania,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>All the Mareschal <hi>de Boussler</hi>'s Journies betwixt <hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>Paris,</hi> and the motions of the Troops so early in the Year upon the Frontiers, were in order to the Descent upon <hi>England;</hi> and the pretended Desertion of so many of the late King <hi>James</hi>'s Servants, on account of their small Allowance, or desire to live in their own Country, under the Rays of a mild Government, was only to prepare things for the present Enterprize.</p>
            <p>We had an Account likewise from <hi>Edinburgh</hi> of <hi>Feb.</hi> 29. that the Plot against His Majesty's Life was entertain'd with the highest resentment there, and that all People express'd their willingness to venture their Lives in defence of His Majesty and the Government: And a Proclamation was Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish'd there, to put the Kingdom in a posture of Defence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Invasion from <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Captain <hi>Stow,</hi> one of those mention'd in the Proclamation, was seiz'd on the 6th, having caus'd himself to be Arrested in a Fob Action of 300 <hi>l.</hi> under the Name of <hi>Smith,</hi> and carried to a Spunging-House, thinking by that means to se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure himself, but a certain Man Arrested for Debt being
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:99011:16"/>brought to that House, knew him, and discover'd him to the Government; by which he got 1000 <hi>l.</hi> to pay his own Debts.</p>
            <p>That same day an Express arrived from Admiral <hi>Russel,</hi> with an Account, That the French were Debarking their Men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in great Consternation; that those of <hi>Calais</hi> were removing their best Effects; and that he could not come at their Men of War because of the cross Winds, but that some of their Transport-Ships being run a-ground were broke by the Waves; and that a large French Privateer being chas'd ashore, run the same Fate.</p>
            <p>The General Officers of the King's Army Subscrib'd the Association that same day, at the Horse-Guards, and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the rest of the Officers to do the like. The Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Land-Tax d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d then also Subscribe the Association.</p>
            <p>Our Bomb-Vessels were detain'd in the River by contrary Winds; and the French, in the mean time, were taking out their Cannon, cutting down their Masts, and endeavouring to Tow their Men of War into <hi>Dunkirk.</hi> One Mr. <hi>Bellasis</hi> was about this time committed to the <hi>Tower</hi> for High-Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son; and Major <hi>Holms,</hi> one of those mentioned in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, was likewise seiz'd.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Tuesday, March</hi> 10. We had this further Account of the Plot, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Conspirators had not only oblig'd themselves by Oath, to the performance of their horrid Design, but took the Sacrament also for a Bond of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cresie; and that, on the <hi>Sunday</hi> before the Plot, one Mr. <hi>Shelton</hi> a Non-jurant, who Preach'd at <hi>Bouthorp,</hi> within a Mile and half of <hi>Norwich,</hi> were he was Patroniz'd by Sir <hi>Robert Yallop,</hi> and frequented by the <hi>Jacobites</hi> from <hi>Norwich,</hi> did, on the <hi>Sunday</hi> before the Plot was to have been put in Execution, Preach on these Words, <hi>Jer.</hi> 24.10. <hi>And I will send the Sword, the Famine, and the Pestilence among them, till they be consum'd from off the Land that I gave unto them and their Fathers.</hi> And on the <hi>Sunday</hi> when the Horrible Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:99011:16"/>was to have been committed, he Preach'd on these Words, <hi>Jer.</hi> 46.10. <hi>For this is the day of the Lord God of Hosts, a day of Vengeance, that he may avenge himself of his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versaries; and the Sword shall devour, and it shall be satiate, and made drunk with their blood, for the Lord God of Hosts hath a Sacrifice in the North Country, by the River</hi> Euphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Sunday</hi> the 8th, two Popish Priests were taken by a Messenger in <hi>Covent-Garden;</hi> they pretended to have the <hi>Portuguese</hi> Ambassadors Protection, and he did accordingly send to demand them, but finding that the Warrant was by Order of Council, and for High-Treason, he made no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther demands.</p>
            <p>That same day a Parson, who had been one of those of <hi>Magdalen</hi>-College in King <hi>James</hi>'s time, and had for some time been at <hi>Marybone,</hi> was taken by a Messenger, who car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying his Maid, and a Young Man with him, on pretence that they came to be Married, took the Parson at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion-Table, just as he was going to read the Marriage-Service.</p>
            <p>That same time we had an Account of a Letter from Mr. <hi>Trinder,</hi> a Noted Justice of Peace in <hi>Middlesex</hi> in King <hi>James</hi>'s time, to his Nephew, a Captain in the E. of <hi>Arran</hi>'s Regiment, Dated at <hi>Paris, Feb.</hi> 7. 1696, as follows:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>SIR, Notwithstanding your great Confidence in your Hero, and your great Ingratitude to your Friend, your Repentance shall not be too late, if the effects of it appear within a Month after the Receipt of this Advertisement. From</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours <hi>J. T.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Captain being in the Country, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was some time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it came to his hand, and he transmitted it to <hi>London,</hi> where it arriv'd the day after the Discovery of the Plot, and was show'd to the Lords and Commons. This discovered a new branch of the Plot, <hi>viz.</hi> That there had been endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours us'd to corrupt the Forces, Mr. <hi>Trinder</hi>'s meaning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:99011:17"/>
               <hi>That his Nephew should join the late King with his Troop.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Government had full Information of the Duke of <hi>Berwick</hi>'s having been at <hi>London,</hi> and of the places where he staid; some said that he was at a Masquerade at <hi>Dropers-Hall,</hi> and the Word of Cabal among some was [<hi>You are Welcome to Town Sir.</hi>] It was also discoursed, That a Commission was found, and lodg'd in the hands of the Government, Sign'd by the late King, to beat up the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Winter Quarters. As also, That <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> and <hi>Pendergrass</hi> did so much contend for the Post of Honour, as they call'd it, to give the Fatal blow to the King, that they fell together by the Ears about it, which did in some measure contribute to the Discovery; for <hi>Pendergrass</hi> absented from the last Club, whereupon the Party suspected him, and design'd to have cut him off, but Captain <hi>Porter,</hi> whom he always call'd Father, because he maintain'd him, having staid behind at the Tavern, chid <hi>Pendergrass</hi> when he came, and giving him an hint of his danger, he did thereupon, as we are inform'd, give Information of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign to the Court, begg'd his own Life and Captain <hi>Porters,</hi> and was very desirous that he himself should not be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd to be Evidence; he acquainted Capt. <hi>Porter</hi> with what he had done, prevail'd with him to concur in the Discovery; and that they might come off from their Party with more Honour, retired into the Country, where they were taken.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Lake,</hi> Minister of St. <hi>Mary-Hill,</hi> being committed to the <hi>Tower</hi> some time before, the occasion of it was found to be a Letter from one <hi>Baron,</hi> a Nonjurant Parson in <hi>Berk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire,</hi> directed to him, and Dated <hi>in the Seventh Year of the Tyrant's Reign,</hi> making mention, that he had sent the Doctor a Chine of Bacon and a Turkey, with many reflect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Expressions; and this amongst others, <hi>That the Dutch Governor had deprived us of all our Money, and we should shortly</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:99011:17"/>have no Victuals; but that in a little time we should rid our hands of him. The said <hi>Baron</hi> was taken a little time after, and brought Prisoner to Town.</p>
            <p>About the same time <hi>Trevor</hi> and <hi>Bryerly,</hi> two of those mentioned in the Proclamation were taken up; as also Parson <hi>Wilcox, Fielding,</hi> commonly called Handsome <hi>Fielding,</hi> and <hi>Blair</hi> a Priest: And some Horses and Arms were seized by the Populace in <hi>Yorkshire.</hi> Mr <hi>Ferguson</hi> noted for his being accused of all the Conspiracies in the Late Reigns, Mr. <hi>Constable,</hi> Brother to the L. <hi>Dumbar,</hi> and several others, were then taken up, and a general Search had been made in the City the Night before.</p>
            <p>The Government took care to reinforce and fortifie <hi>Landguard</hi> Fort; Admiral <hi>Russel</hi> got the Association sign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Fleet; and one who had listed Men for the late King, giving them a Guinea Advance-Money, and 5 <hi>s. per</hi> Week Subsistance, was taken up.</p>
            <p>On Thursday <hi>March</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th, we had an account that the Earl of <hi>Athlone,</hi> with the Generals <hi>Coehorn</hi> and <hi>Swerin,</hi> had march'd to <hi>Givet,</hi> with 25000 Horse and Foot, 10 Guns and 12 Mortars, and having thrown in red hot Bullets from 8 Furnaces, and 500 Bombs from their Mortars, they destroyed the vast Magazines of Forage, Provision and Ammunition, which the <hi>French</hi> had laid up there, amounting to three Millions of Rations, being as much as would have served all their Cavalry in <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> and the Neighbouring Provinces, during the Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagne; and that the <hi>French</hi> reckoned themselves so sure of their design on the King of <hi>Great Britains</hi> Life, that their King intended to have been at <hi>Mons</hi> in Person on the 25th of <hi>March,</hi> and to have Encamp'd a Great Army near <hi>Hall,</hi> either to have carried on some Siege of Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, or to have invaded <hi>Flanders,</hi> as they should have found most convenient; and that all the Bisket which
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:99011:18"/>they had been Baking and Packing up in Hogsheads for two Months, was designed for the Expedition against <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That same Mail brought us an account that the <hi>French</hi> Court were unwilling to own the Miscarriage of the said Design, but pretended that they could not Embark be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of the Low-Water, and that they waited only for a Spring Tide; and that they had remitted 50000 Pistols more to King <hi>James</hi> at <hi>Calais.</hi> They were so very confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of their Success, that at <hi>Montroyal, Treves, Dinant,</hi> and other of their Frontier Towns, they gave out that King <hi>William</hi> was kill'd as a Hunting, that it was impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible their Design should miscarry; and that now they should be able to make such a diversion in <hi>Germany</hi> and the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> as will oblige the Allies to accept of a Peace upon their Terms. We had also Advices from <hi>Hamborough,</hi> that Captain <hi>Graham</hi> had stole a Ship there, and Listed twenty Men for King <hi>James</hi> to steal more; whereupon the Government had writ to <hi>England</hi> to know whether they would have him tryed there, or sent over hither.</p>
            <p>Our Letters from <hi>Edenburgh</hi> of the 6th of <hi>March</hi> gave an account, that the Earl of <hi>Hame,</hi> Earl of <hi>Strathmore,</hi> Lord <hi>Drumcairn,</hi> Lord <hi>Drummond,</hi> Sir <hi>William Sharp,</hi> Sir <hi>William Bruce,</hi> and others, were taken up there to prevent their raising any Rebellion; and the Privy Council of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the City of <hi>Edenburgh</hi> sent very Loyal Addresses to the King, offering to stand by him with their Lives and Fortunes against all His Enemies at Home and Abroad.</p>
            <p>At the same time Eight or Nine Regiments arrived in the River from <hi>Flanders,</hi> but were kept on Board, there being no probability of our having any need of them.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:99011:18"/>
            <p> On the Tuesday before Sir <hi>William Perkins,</hi> mentioned in the Proclamation, was taken in a Gentlemans Chamber over the <hi>Crown-Office</hi> in the <hi>Temple:</hi> Captain <hi>Lothier,</hi> Major <hi>Soper,</hi> and others, were also taken about this time.</p>
            <p>Letters from <hi>Norwich</hi> gave an account that the <hi>Jacobites</hi> and <hi>Papists</hi> of that Country were mightily elevated before the discovery of the Plot, and gave out that their King would return before <hi>Easter,</hi> but after the discovery they lookt as if they had been Thunder-struck.</p>
            <p>There were also Letters from <hi>Weymouth,</hi> that one Lieutenant <hi>Wroth</hi> of a Press-Ketch, did on the first News of the discovery tell it openly, that he had received a Letter from one <hi>Tooth</hi> at <hi>London,</hi> with these words in it, <hi>The King of a sudden is fallen Ill, I will give you a further Account in my next.</hi> Whereupon <hi>Wroth</hi> was taken, and sent up to <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On Wednesday the 11th, the Tryals of <hi>Charnock, Keyse,</hi> and <hi>King,</hi> commenced at the <hi>Old Baily;</hi> and the Witnesses being Capt. <hi>Porter, Pendergrass, de la Rue, Bertram</hi> and <hi>Boyse,</hi> It was Sworn that <hi>Charnock</hi> communicated the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign of Killing the King to <hi>Porter,</hi> and told him, that Sir <hi>George Barclay,</hi> and some others, had brought a Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion from K. <hi>James,</hi> Writ and Signed with his own Hand for doing it; that he offered to acquaint <hi>Porter</hi> with Sir <hi>George,</hi> and told him, that Sir <hi>William Perkins</hi> had read the Commission. It was also Sworn, that they had seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Consults upon it, and design d to have perpetrated the Horrid Fact on the 10th or 15th of <hi>February;</hi> that <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> and <hi>Durance</hi> were appointed as Spies at <hi>Kensington,</hi> the one to give Notice when the Guards went, and the other to give Notice of the Kings going from thence; That some proposed to do it on Horse-back, but Sir <hi>Geo. Barclay</hi> was for doing it on Foot; upon which they sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:99011:19"/>the execution till they viewed the Ground; for which end <hi>Porter</hi> and <hi>King</hi> went over the River, viewed the Roads, and resolved upon the end of a Lane by. <hi>Turnham-Green,</hi> and some Pales were to have been pulled down to make the Attempt more easie upon the Kings return from <hi>Richmond;</hi> That several Consults were held upon this, wherein they came to a fixt Resolution to do it on Horse-back by 45 Persons; Sir <hi>VVilliam Perkins,</hi> Sir <hi>George Barclay, Charnock</hi> and <hi>Perter,</hi> being each to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure their number; That they were to be divided into two Parties, the Greater Commanded by Sir <hi>George,</hi> to attack the Guards, and the Lesser by <hi>Porter,</hi> to Murder the King; for the easier effecting of which, they were to kill some of His Coach-Horses first; That Sir <hi>George Barclay</hi> brought Money from <hi>France</hi> to buy Horses, twenty of which were actually purchased, and the rest were to be hired; That the Horrid Design being effected, Sir <hi>George</hi> was to take Post for <hi>Dover,</hi> and hasten to <hi>Calais</hi> to King <hi>James,</hi> who was to have ordered five thousand Men to land in the <hi>North,</hi> and he himself in Person was to have landed in <hi>Sussex</hi> or <hi>Kent;</hi> That the 10th of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary</hi> was the day appointed, but having received no Notice from their Spies at <hi>Kensington,</hi> it was deferred to the 15th, when one of them gave notice that the Guards were gone, and then they prepared for the Attempt with great Joy; but upon Advice that the Guards were return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in haste, they suspected that the thing had taken Air. It was also Sworn, that the Matter had been in agitation three Years, and was always revived upon the Kings re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn from <hi>Flanders. De la Rue,</hi> one of the Evidence, said that he would have discovered it last Year, if it had drawn to a head; but perceiving it ripe in <hi>February</hi> last, he acquainted Brigadier <hi>Lewson</hi> therewith, who carried him to the King, and advised that His Majesty should go
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:99011:19"/>to <hi>Richmond</hi> accordingly, and send two Troops to secure the whole Party. It was also Sworn, that <hi>Pendergrass</hi> was introduc'd to make his discovery much about that same time, and advised His Majesty not to go thither on the 15th: That the Road betwixt <hi>Hide-Park</hi> and St. <hi>James</hi>'s-<hi>Park,</hi> was also proposed as a fit place for the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt: That it had been debated amongst them, whether or not they should carry the King into <hi>France,</hi> but that <hi>Charnock</hi> gave his Opinion, that the Little Spark must be taken out of the Way, and then King <hi>James</hi> would come in easily: That it was also proposed▪ that Sir <hi>VVilliam Perkins</hi> should raise a Regiment of House for the design, and that the Prisoner should furnish Men; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> said that such a number would be too great to keep the Secret, unless it were speedily put in Execution. It was Sworn particularly against <hi>King,</hi> that he gave one of the Evidence a Blunderbuss that would early eight Bullets, for the Horrid Attempt. And in short, the design of the Assassination was so clearly proved against all the three, that after a full hearing the Jury brought them in Guilty; and Sentence was past upon them as usual in Cases of High Treason; on which the People gave a Great Huzza.</p>
            <p>On Wednesday <hi>March</hi> the 18th, <hi>Char<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ock, King,</hi> and <hi>K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yes,</hi> the three Condemned Assassins, were drawn on a Hurdle from <hi>Newgate</hi> to <hi>Tyburn,</hi> where they ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d the design of Assassinating the King, and delivered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ch a Paper to the Sheriffs, who were observed to carry them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves towards them with a generous Compassion. The Criminals were Executed according to the Sentence, and their Quarters brought back to <hi>Newgate.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:99011:20"/>
            <p> In the Evening the Sheriffs attended the King with the Papers which they received from the Criminals; which Papers contain a full and positive Confession of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign'd Assassination, (or in Mr. <hi>Charnocks</hi> own words, <hi>To Attack the Prince of</hi> Orange <hi>and his Guards</hi>) but are not so clear as to that part of it which relates to King <hi>James</hi>'s Commission; however, it is not doubted but the fame will be proved in a few days.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Charnock</hi> says, As concerning the Invasion by King <hi>James</hi> upon <hi>England,</hi> that there was certain Intelligence of it Abroad.</p>
            <p>And Mr. <hi>King</hi> owns, that he was brought to that place by the Just Hand of God in Punishment of all his Crimes, and particularly of that of which he had been lately Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned, and for which he stood there Condemned.</p>
            <p>It's observable, that the Criminals dyed Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, and declined the Assistance of any Protestant Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster; and that <hi>Charnock</hi> perform'd the last Offices for himself and the other two.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 12. Line 20. for <hi>Sunday</hi> read <hi>Saturday.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:99011:20"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books newly Printed for</hi> John Salusbury, <hi>at the</hi> Rising Sun <hi>in</hi> Cornhill.</head>
            <p>A Compleat French Master for Ladies and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: or an exact New Grammar, to learn with Ease and Delight the French Tongue, as it is now spoken in the Court of <hi>France;</hi> wherein is to be seen an Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary and Methodical Order for the acquisition of that Tongue. Enriched with new Words, and the most modish Pronunciation, and all the Advantages and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements of that famous Language. Written for his Highness the Duke of <hi>Glocester.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Universal Redemption of Mankind by the Lord Jesus Christ, stated and cleared by the late Learned Mr. <hi>Rich. Baxter:</hi> Also a short account of Special Redemption by the same Author. Published by Mr. <hi>Matthew Sylvester,</hi> and Mr. <hi>J. Read.</hi> Price 4 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eachards Gazetteers,</hi> or <hi>Newsmans Interpreters,</hi> being a Geographical Index of all Cities, Towns, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in <hi>Europe,</hi> with their distances from each other, and to what Prince they are now subject; very necessary for the right under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing of all Forreign and Domestick News Letters and Gazetts. 12. Price bound 2 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:99011:21"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A most Compleat Compondium of Geography, General and Special,</hi> describing all the Empires, Kingdoms and Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions in the whole World, collected according to the latest Discoveries, and agreeing with the choicest and newest Maps. 12. Price bound 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Exact Description of</hi> Ireland, Surveying all its Provinces and Counties; shewing the exact state of that Kingdom, and all the principal Things that are necessary to be known; Illustrated with five Maps, one of the whole Kingdom, the other of each particular Province, 12. bound, Price 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:99011:21"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>